Alexander Skoglund, Ph.D. (1976-02-28)

Contact Stopvägen 86 Mobile: +46 (0)72-077 17 34

Information 16836 Bromma E-mail: alexander.skoglund@e2labs.eu

Sweden

EXPERIENCE SUMMARY

Methods

Scientific and engineering skills: Robotics, scientific methods, machine learning, computer vision, computer graphics, scientific writing, real time programming, embedded systems.

Programming languages: C and C++, MATLAB (and GNU Octave) and Python (basic user).

Electronics: System design, analogue design, filter design, PCB design (prototype and production),

test and measurement, board bring-up. Work methods: Agile (scrum) and lean.

Tools

Software development: GNU eco system (GCC for ARM/AVR/MSP430, make, gdb, openood, avrdude), Atmel Studio, Microchip's XC compiler, IAR Workbench, VSCode, Emacs, Eclipse (multiple derivatives), Jenkins and Unity for Unit testing.

Host environment: GNU/Linux since 2002. Several years of experience with Apple's OSX.

Version management: Git (Bitbucket, Github, Gerrit) and Subversion.

Documenting: JIRA, LATEX, Doxygen and Wikis.

Protocols: I²C, SPI, UART, RS232, CAN, USB, TCP/IP sockets.

Electronic design: LTSpice, CadSoft Eagle, KiCad, gerbview.

Instrument: Multimeter, oscilloscope, logical analyser, protocol analyser, surface mounted soldering.

Misc: ROS, OpenGL, OpenCV, firewire.

Microcontrollers and boards ARM Cortex M4 (XMC44XX, STM32F4), ARM Cortex M0 (Blue-NRG), AVR (STK500, Arduino etc.), MSP430 (TI LaunchPad), STM8 and Microchip dsPIC33EP.

Currently learning: NodeJS and KiCad.

Present Position Scarreco, Stockholm, Sweden

Senior Embedded Systems Engineer

From 2019-04

Working with firmware for the next generation of Scanreco's professional remote controls. Primarily working with the Bluetooth connectivity for firmware upgrades (bootloaders) and remote configuration with back end.

Professional

Realtime Embedded, Stockholm, Sweden

EXPERIENCE

Firmware/hardware engineer

From 2017-03 - 2019-03

Working with electronics and firmware design for RTE's clients. Primarily working on system design and firmware for hardware interaction, and also electronic development and board bring-up. The largest project involved power control, CAN communication and bootloading (among others).

BioServo Technologies, Stockholm, Sweden

Firmware/hardware engineer

From 2014-02 - 2017-02

Working on electronic and firmware design on BioServo's SEM glove and next generation of BioServo's products. Primarily working on electronic development, board bring-up, system design and firmware for hardware interaction. Responsible for software in a scientific project to evaluate BioServo's product. Also maintaining current production version with upgrades and production support.

ÅF Group, Stockholm, Sweden Embedded Software Eng.

2012 - 11 - 2014 - 02

Working on firmware design for client's embedded systems. Project 1: embedded Linux on ARM for an autonomous mobile robot. Project 2: embedded Linux web server on a RaspberryPi, short investigation and demo mock-up. Project 3: PWM control using an MSP430, short investigation. Project 4: control of an electrochromic foil (AVR) and powerline communication (LonTalk), 9 months.

Karolinska Institute, Research Engineer, Stockholm, Sweden

2009-12 - 2012-11

Research Engineer in Brain, Body & Self Laboratory (Ehrsson group), at the Department of Neuroscience. My main task was to develop custom electronics and software for research in neuroscience. I worked on developing an MR compatible robotic anthropomorphic hand for neuroscience research on body perception, body ownership, agency, and prosthesis.

Örebro University, Research Assistant, Örebro, Sweden

2009-06 - 2009-12

Work on modelling of human grasping strategies. Modelled grasping skills should be possible to transfer to dexterous robotic hand. This work is part of the HANDLE project, funded by EU:s FP7.

Örebro University, Ph.D Student, Örebro, Sweden

Nov, 2003 – June, 2009

Research on Programming-by-Demonstration including learning systems, human-machine interfaces, human-like motions. In addition, I have been a teaching assistant in several courses. On parental leave in 2008-02–2008-05 and 2008-12–2009-01 (50%).

Örebro University, Research engineer, Örebro, Sweden

June, 2001 – Nov, 2003

Maintenance with mobile robots and lightweight manipulators. Also, involved in the electronic design of an electronic tongue for water quality assessment, control system for manipulators, range finding sonar for manipulation.

Aerotech Telub, Radio engineer, Arboga, Sweden

Jan, 2000 – June, 2001

Carried out several consulting projects associated with a short range radio for the take off team around the fighter aircraft SAAB JAS Gripen. I was involved in preliminary radio measurements for installation of a radio system in the metro of Barcelona.

Courses

Non academic courses

- Nov. 26–27, 2019 Machine safety
- Maj 16, 2019 How to Develop Better Firmware Faster by Jack Ganssle
- Apr. 23–24, 2013 Building the IoT with Thingsquare Mist and Contiki

EDUCATION

Örebro University, Örebro, Sweden

- Ph.D., Computer Science, Programming by Demonstration of Robot Manipulators 2009.
- M.Sc., Electrical and Electronic Engineering, December 2002.
- B.A., Electrical Engineering, September 1998.

Academic skills

During my Ph.D. my research field was within imitation learning, where a robot learns a task by observing a human. Learning should then continue to improve the performance by further self-observation or by providing more knowledge from the demonstrator (teacher). The main application is to simplify the programming process of an industrial manipulator (robot arm), a.k.a. "Programming-by-Demonstration".

Teaching class

September 2009 - December 2009

Introduction to Robotics and Intelligent Systems, Master Course. Autumn 2009. An introductory course in robotics. Topics covered: Robotic history, actuators, manipulation, sensing and perception, localisation, navigation, mapping, state estimation, dead reckoning, Bayesian filters and multi robot applications.

Teaching Assistant

August 2004 - January 2008

Duties at various times have included office hours and leading weekly computer lab exercises.

- TDD121/PRG045 Programming in C, Winter 2006 and 2007.
- TDM136 Methods for Modelling, Simulation and Visualisation, Fall 2007.
- TDD112 Computer Graphics, Fall and Autumn 2004, Autumn 2005, Fall 2006, Fall 2007.